Guide to the Rights and Wrongs Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Programs, 1993-1996; Series IV
  - Human Rights in Northern Ireland, 1994 April 9; 202
    The program consists of segments on an examination of the conflict in Northern Ireland and its impact on issues including jobs, housing, and the vote; a commentary by Andrew Tyndall on why the networks are more interested in the troubles of the House of Windsor than the troubles in Northern Ireland; a exclusive interview with Bernadette Devlin McAliskey; and reports from Sarajevo with a commentary by Pulitzer Prize-winning New York Times reporter John Burns.
    - Master, 1 (Box 141)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 141D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 141U)
  - South Africa: a Human Rights Success Story, 1994 April 16; 203
    The program consists of a report on politically inspired violence threatening the transition to a multi-racial democracy; an interview with Judge Richard Goldstone, the head of the judicial commission, which revealed a conspiracy at senior levels of South Africa's security forces to sabotage the transition to majority rule; excerpts from Mama Awethu, a film by Bethany Yarrow about women in South Africa; and a music video of a multi-racial group singing "Freedom Charter," a song about the struggle to end apartheid.
    - Master, 1 (Box 142)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 142D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 142U)
  - Africa: the Uncovered Continent, 1994 April 23; 204
    The program consists of segments on Reverend Beyers Naude, a remarkable Afrikaner, once part of the apartheid establishment, who now speaks publicly against it; an interview with Kenyan human rights activist Wangari Maathai, with a rebuttal from Kenyan Ambassador Don Nanjira; a report from Rwanda with representatives from African Rights and Amnesty International; and excerpts from features and documentaries from the Human Rights Watch Film Festival.
    - Master, 1 (Box 143)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 143D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 143U)
  - The United Nations and Human Rights, 1994 April 30; 205
    The program consists of segments on the status of the UN's human rights mandate in light of its Peacekeeping Operations in Bosnia, Somalia, and El Salvador; an interview with Kofi Annan, Under-Secretary-General of UN Peacekeeping Operations; an interview with Anna Deavere Smith, writer, performer, social commentator, and star of her own one woman show, "Twilight: Los Angeles 1992"; Hungary's nationalist movement; and the Black Audio Film Collective's examination of Black and Afro-Caribbean experience in the United Kingdom.
    - Master, 1 (Box 144)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 144D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 144U)
  - Myanmar: the 'Keep Quiet' Regime, 1994 May 7; 206
    The program consists of segments on "the human rights crisis in Myanmar", an examination of the documented human rights abuses by the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC); an interview with Kenneth Roth, Executive Director of Human Rights Watch, about ethnic warfare, new ways to link trade and human rights, and how the Clinton Administration is viewed by human rights activists; a look inside New York City's El Puente Academy of Peace and Justice; and music video of Romanian musicians singing about revolution.
    - Master, 1 (Box 145)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 145D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 145U)
  - Trade and Human Rights, 1994 May 14; 207
    The program consists of segments on President Nelson Mandela discussing his plan to forge a "government of national unity" in South Africa; the controversy surrounding the linking of trade to human rights policy, particularly with regard to China's "Most Favored Nation" status, with comments by Henry Kissinger, Lane Kirkland, the Dalai Lama, US Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights John Shattuck, and former Chinese political prisoner Wang Juntao; and excerpts from " Satya: a Prayer for the Enemy ," a film which explores the spiritual resistance of Tibetan nuns persecuted by their Chinese occupiers.
    - Master, 1 (Box 146)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 146D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 146U)
  - Human Rights in the Occupied Territories, 1994 May 21; 208
    The program consists of segments on the tranisition to Palestinian self-rule in parts of the Israeli-occupied territories; efforts of field workers from two different but complementary human rights groups--one Palestinian, the other Israeli; an interview with Hanan Ashrawi, one time Palestinian peace negotiator and head of a Palestinian human rights group; Allen Ginsberg reading his newest poem, "Peace in Bosnia-Herzegovina"; and a music video of Yothu Yindi, a predominantly aboriginal band of musicians from Australia
    - Master, 1 (Box 147)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 147D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 147U)
  - The Media and Human Rights, 1994 May 28; 209
    The program consists of segments on the lack of media independence in post-communist Hungary where broadcast media came under attack by the government for its "liberal bias"; commentary by Andrew Tyndall on how the media covers itself; the growing number of journalists who are killed while on assignment; the world's most unusual radio station, Belgrade's B-92, which mixes music with anti-war activism in Serbia's Capital.
    - Master, 1 (Box 148)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 148D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 148U)
  - Haiti, 1994 June 4; 210
    The program consists of segments on the political situation in Haiti; an nterview with exiled Haitian President Jean Bertrand Aristide; highlights form David Korb's film, The Other Haiti, about grass roots democratic movements there; Andrew Tyndall on television news coverage of Haiti; and the Haitian peasant democracy movement and its music.
    - Master, 1 (Box 149)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 149D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 149U)
  - Children and Human Rights I, 1994 June 11; 211
    The program consists of segments on the conditions of children around the world; a rap video written and performed by students at El Puente Academy for Peace and Justice, in Brooklyn; a rofile of a 13 year old African-American boy who lives in Washington, DC; a profile of a 15 year old girl in India; the recent brutality against Brazilian street children; Andrew Tyndall on television news coverage of children and human rights; and Judy Collins' song, I Dream of Peace, accompanied by drawings and writings of children living with war.
    - Master, 1 (Box 150)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 150D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 150U)
  - Human Rights in North America, 1994 June 18; 212
    The program consists of segments on Mississippi's "Freedom Summer," when the civil rights struggle for the right of African Americans to vote brought worldwide attention to human rights abuses in the United States; Canada's hydroelectric project at James Bay spawns conflict between indigenous peoples and the state-owned energy company; the US Army's School of the Americas in Georgia trains soldiers, some of whom have become Latin America's worst dictators; Andrew Tyndall on the United States media's coverage of Native Americans; Haile Germia's feature film, Sankofa, offers a new view of slavery in America; and the director talks about his work and the difficulty of making such a film.
    - Master, 1 (Box 151)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 151D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 151U)
  - Child Prostitution in Thailand, 1994 June 25; 213
    The program consists of segments on an examination of Thailand's burgeoning, multi-billion dollar, sex industry and the sexual trafficking of minors; an exerpt form the film, Cuba Va, shows the diversity of opinion held by Cuban youths about the Revolution; Nobel Peace Prize winner Rigoberta Menchu, who fights for the rights of indigenous people in Guatemanla and around the world; and the impact of American Rap and Rock and Roll on the Cuban music scene
    - Master, 1 (Box 152)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 152D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 152U)
  - Tajikistan, 1994 July 1; 214
    The program consists of segments on the former Soviet Republic of Tajikistan, where the civil war has taken an estimanted 50,000 lives and has resulted in summary execution, disappearances, and ethnic strife; Father Ricardo Rezende and his work defending poor, landless peasants in the Brazilian Amazon; Peacewatch, an ongoing chronicle of the global effort to define peacemanking an to examine the interplay of conflict resolution and human rights; forced labor in Burma; the International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Awards; and excerpts form Chelyabinsk: The Most Contaminated Spot on the Planet, and an interview with Slawomir Grunberg on the relationship between human rights and the environment.
    - Master, 1 (Box 153)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 153D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 153U)
  - Tolerance, 1995 March 21; 301
    The program consists of segments on Los Angeles' attempts to promote tolerance; an interview with controversial author and philosopher Cornel West; a profile of human rights hero and children's conflict resolution educator Darryl Williams, who was paralyzed by a sniper's bullet during Boston's 1979 busing crisis.
    - Master, 1 (Box 154)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 154D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 154U)
  - Children and Human Rights II, 1995; 302
    The program consists of segments on Geoffrey Canada directing Harlem's Rheedlen Centers for Children & Families which provides quality preventive social services to New York City's most devastated communities; an Appalachian youth and former skinhead talking about how his life was turned around by a group called Appalshop; and an interview with Marian Wright Edelman, Founder and Director of the Children's Defense Fund.
    - Master, 1 (Box 155)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 155D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 155U)
  - Human Rights and Land Rights, 1995; 303
    The program consists of segments on filmmaker Geoffrey O'Connor's Academy Award-nominated story of the Waiapi people of Brazil, At the Edge of Conflict, which offers an inside look at the struggle of indigenous people and their leader, Chief Wai-Wai, to survive the encroachment of developers and regain legal title to their traditional lands; and Indigenous peoples around the world fight for land rights.
    - Master, 1 (Box 156)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 156D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 156U)
  - South Africa, 1995 April 19; 304
    The program marks the anniversary of Nelson Mandela's 1994 election with segments on an American/South African co-production, Countdown to Freedom: Ten Days that Changed South Africa, narrated by James Earl Jones and Alfre Woodard; an interview with Dr. Makaziwe Mandela, President Mandela's eldest daughter and the University of Witswatersrand's advisor on Affirmative Action/Equal Opportunity; return to Robben Islan Prison - 1200 former prisoners join together at this Cape Town prison for a reunion; and a music Video with Rap group, Prophets of the City, singing "Never Again".
    - Master, 1 (Box 157)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 157D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 157U)
  - Child Labor I, 1995 April 25; 305
    The program consists of segments on The Carpet, a documentary film by Swedish director Magnus Bergmar that looks at Pakistan's system of child labor and the movement to abolish it; an update on the short life and tragic death of Iqbal Masih, featuring footage from his funeral and charges that his death was part of a conspiracy against him by Pakistan's carpet "mafia", and an interview with UNICEF Deputy Executive Director Guido Bertolaso
    - Master, 1 (Box 158)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 158D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 158U)
  - Rwanda: After the Genocide, 1995 May 2; 306
    The program consists of segment on what has happened since the genocide violence in Rwanda; a Rwandan wedding ceremony: the birth of a new family facilities the healing of a community; and an interview with Ken Roth, Executive Director of Human Rights Watch, on the impact war crimes tribunals have had in Rwanda and around the world.
    - Master, 1 (Box 159)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 159D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 159U)
  - Human Rights in Asia, 1995 May 9; 307
    The program consists of segments on Moving the Mountain, directed by Michael Apted and produced by Trudie Styler; an interview with Li Lu, a former student leader, now living in exile, on the decline of human rights in China; and From Hollywood to Hanoi, where Vietnamese-American filmmaker journeys back to Vietnam to understand her own feelings about the war. She visits My Lai, the site of a massacre by American troops, to make an appeal for reconciliation and friendship.
    - Master, 1 (Box 160)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 160D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 160U)
  - Human Rights and Cuba, 1995 May 17; 308
    The program consists of segments on an interview with US Under Secretary of State Peter Tarnoff, Washington's top negotiator, and Edgardo Valdes, a representative of the Cuban Government at the United Nations, on the nature of the changing US-Cuban relations, and its impact on human rights; Emmy Award-winning film maker Hon Alpert, reports from Cuba on the state of Cuba and Cuban-American relations form the vantage point of ordinary Cubans; and an interview with two Cuban-Americans, Frank Calzon of Freedom House (a long time critic of Castro's policies) and Sam Farber, writer for the Campaign for Peace & Democracy about their opposing positions on the United States embargo.
    - Master, 1 (Box 161)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 161D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 161U)
  - Human Rights and Islam, 1995 May 24; 309
    The program consists of segments on Algerian conflict between an authoritarian government and an insurgent Islamist movement; independent producer Susan Mazur, going behind the lines in Kashmir to report on the conflict's mounting death toll and its human rights implications; children's impressions of the war in Sarejevo, produced by Ademir Kenovic and the SAGA film company; and women under Islamic law speaking out and calling for an end to second class citizenship.
    - Master, 1 (Box 162)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 162D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 162U)
  - The Yellow Wasps: Roots of Ethnic Cleansing [part I], 1995 May 31; 310
    The program consists of an extended excerpt from the documentray Yellow Wasps, directed by Ilan Ziv and produced by Rory O'Connor, examines ethnic cleansing in the former Yugoslavia through a war crimes trial of a Serbian para-military group called "Yellow Wasps" and jounalists and survivors relating their personal experiences.
    - Master, 1 (Box 163)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 163D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 163U)
  - The Yellow Wasps: Roots of Ethnic Cleansing [part II], 1995 June 7; 311
    The program examines the discovery of concentration camps and response of the international community; and Charlayne Hunter-Gault questions former U.S. Secretary of State, Lawrence Eagleburger, on the moral implications of non-intervention
    - Master, 1 (Box 164)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 164D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 164U)
  - Health and Human Rights, 1995 June 14; 312
    The program consists of Jonathan Mann, architect of the World Health Organization's program on AIDS, exploring the connection between health and human rights; and an interview with Yale Law School's Prof. Harlan Dalton and Prof. Karen Porter, who teaches law and medicine at Washington University.
    - Master, 1 (Box 165)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 165D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 165U1)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 165U2)
  - Peace and Conflict Resolution, 1995 June 21; 313
    The program consists of segments on "Tomorrow's Leaders" conference held in Venice, Italy, and sponsored by Nobel Laureate, Elie Wiesel, where young people from Northern Ireland, the former Yugoslavia, Africa, the Middle East and the United States, join seasoned foreign diplomats in discussion about tolerance, dialogue and negotiations; an interview with Holocaust survivor Elie Wiesel on the importance of dialogue; and PS 230 in Brooklyn, New York, an elementary school where students learn conflict resolution techinques in an effort to prevent violence and promote tolerance.
    - Master, 1 (Box 166)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 166D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 166U)
  - Torture, Rehabilitation/Land Mines/New Technologies, 1995 June 30; 319
    The program consists of segments on the Centers for Victims of Torture in Minneapolis, MN and in Toronto, Canada; Are We the Enemy?, a report on how an estimated 8 to 10 million active land mines are affecting the lives of Cambodians who, because of these mines, have the highest number of handicapped people per capita in the world, produced by the Women's Media Centre of Cambodia and Media Ties Inc; and New Technologies, a report on how human rights groups like Amnesty, HR Watch and Peacenet/IGC are using computers, CD-Rom's and the Internet to link up worldwide.
    - Master, 1 (Box 167)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 167D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 167U)
  - Snakeheads: Chinese 'People Smugglers', 1996 April 17; 401
    The program consists of nine-time Emmy Award winning journalist Jon Alpert traveling to China's Fujian province, where people agree to pay more than $30,000 to smugglers, or 'snakeheads,' who will sneak them into the United States. Once in the US many of these immigrants face long stays in INS detention, an inability to find work, except in sweatshops, illegally low pay and horrid living conditions. Includes an interview with refugee expert, Arthur Helton and award-winning journalist, Ying Chan, about the issue.
    - Master, 1 (Box 168)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 168D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 168U)
  - Chechnya-Russia's Human Rights Nightmare, 1996 May 1; 402
    The program consists of segments on the ongoing conflict in Russia, with comment from Sergei Kovalev, Russia's former commissioner of Human Rights, and Ludmilla Thorne, a human rights specialist at Freedom House; Thomas Goltz's "video diary" about the village of Somashki and its efforts to defend itself from the Russian army's assault; and an exclusive interview with Fred Cuny, a disaster relief specialist and human rights hero who traveled to Chechnya in 1995 and has been missing and presumed dead ever since.
    - Master, 1 (Box 169)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 169D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 169U)
  - Israel and Palestine: At the Edge of Peace?, 1996 May 9; 403
    The program consists of segments on a Palestinian living in a refugee camp and an Israeli settler living a few miles away, who taped "video diaries" recording their perspectives on the ongoing peace process in the Middle East from 1993 to 1996; and an interview with Terje Larsen, whose creative peacemaking role and spectacular results led to his appointment as Undersecretary-General to the United Nations and Special Coordinator in the Occupied Territories.
    - Master, 1 (Box 170)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 170D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 170U)
  - The Media and Human Rights, 1996 May 14; 404
    The program consists of segments on the media's shrinking coverage of international news and its impact on human rights with an interview with media analyst Noam Chomsky and a look at the role of new tools and technologies--low cost video cameras, computers, and the internet--in human rights activism, a phenomenon which some have termed "weapons of mass communication."
    - Master, 1 (Box 171)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 171D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 171U)
  - Global Institutions and Human Rights, 1996 May 17; 405
    The program consists of segments on institutions like the United Nations, the World Bank, the International Monetary Fund, and NATO in a post-Cold War context; the World Bank activities in Mexico and their impact on the daily lives of ordinary Mexican citizens; and an interview with UN Assistant Secretary General Alvaro de Soto.
    - Master, 1 (Box 172)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 172D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 172U)
  - Women's Rights as Human Rights, 1996 May 29; 406
    The program consists of segments on women's rights globally and within the United States; feminist/activist Bella Abzug reflecting on the growing empowerment of non-governmental organizations and the strategies that made the outcome of the Beijing Conference so successful; three grassroots organizers from Bangladesh, Zimbabwe, and the United States discussing their work and how women's issues are linked globally; and an interview with Vandana Shiva, an Indian environmentalist and women's activist.
    - Master, 1 (Box 173)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 173D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 173U)
  - Safe Havens [part I], 1996 June 5; 407
    The Safe Havens programs examine the fall of Srebrenica, a town in Bosnia declard a "safe have" under UN protection and ccontain interviews with former State Department Ambassador at Large, Robert Gallucci, and Newsday correspondent and Pulitzer Prize winner, Roy Gutman, about the lessons of the fall of Srebrenica.
    - Master, 1 (Box 174)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 174D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 174U)
  - Safe Havens [part II], 1996 June 13; 408
    - Master, 1 (Box 175)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 175D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 175U)
  - Peace and Conflict Resolution, 1996 June 19; 409
    The program consists of excerpts on Leap of Faith, a documentary about segregated Northern Ireland, where parents have created an integrated school of Catholics and Protestants to begin the process of religious and political reconciliation; Seeds of Peace, a documentary focusing on a unique summer camp in Maine, where young Israelis and Palestinians learn to understand each other and resolve differences constructively; and an interview with Archishop Desmond Tutu about South Africa's Truth and Reconciliation Commission, its mandate to expose the crimes of apartheid and to promote reconciliation in a long-divided South Africa.
    - Master, 1 (Box 176)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 176D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 176U)
  - Children and Human Rights III, 1996 June 26; 410
    The program consists of segments on the "STAND FOR CHILDREN' rally, where hundreds of thousands of Americans and children's rights advocates gathered in Washington, DC; the Denmark Children's Council, one of the first attempts to bring the voice of children directly into the seat of government; and Yasmin, a street child from India, showing her world and the importance of education through her personal video diary.
    - Master, 1 (Box 177)
    - Duplicating master, 1 videotape (Betacam-SP) (Box 177D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 177U)
  - Heroes of Human Rights, 1996 July 3; 411